Harrison Yocum Papers 1864-2010 (bulk 1953-2008)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Harrison Yocum Papers 1864-2010 (bulk 1953-2008)
MS 572
Yocum,Harrison
This collection is centered on Yocum’s academic and professional interests in horticulture, botany and geology as well as his personal interests in musical composition, his family’s history and Christian religion and his role in the creation and development of Tucson Botanical Gardens. Items included in the collection are his notes on botany, research into palm trees, publications, autobiographical and family history information, press clippings; records regarding the Rockhounds, the Arizona branch of the International Palm Society and Tucson Botanical Gardens.
9.9 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/ E-Mail: LBRY-askspcoll@email.arizona.edu
Restrictions
No restrictions.
Biographical Note
Harrison Yocum (1923-2010) studied horticulture with a minor in botany at Penn State, graduating in 1955 then earning his MS in Botany at Rutgers in 1959. A lifelong botanist and horticulturalist, Harrison Yocum had a large collection of palm trees when he moved to Tucson from Bethlehem, PA in 1964. In Tucson he worked at the Dendrochronology Lab at the University of Arizona (UA). He moved on to supervising landscaping at Tucson International Airport (TIA), winning a number of awards for his work there. His home became the first site of the Tucson Botanical Gardens before it moved temporarily to Reid Park and finally to the Porter family’s nursery on Alvernon Way in 1975.
After retiring from TIA in 1982, he taught classes in geology at Pima Community College, organizing the Pima College Rockhounds’ field trips. Yocum led field trips to collect geologic samples far afield in southern Arizona, producing handouts with his whimsical original ink drawings and maps. His students at Pima College along with returning friends and students were referred to as the Pima College Rockhounds (which he also rendered as Rock Hounds and Rock-hounds; we have preserved his usage).
Harrison Yocum also had extensive training in music starting at about the time he graduated high school. He wrote 195 original compositions for piano which are also included in this collection, including his favorite piece, The Cardboard Mountains.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into seven series
Series 1: Work in Botany, Work in Botany, 1950-2010
Sub-Series 1: Academic and Professional Work, 1951-1989
Sub-Series 2: Work on Palm Trees, 1950-1986
Sub-Series 3: Tucson Botanical Gardens, 1964-2010
Series 2: Work and Teaching in Geology, 1976-2010
Sub-Series 1: Records of the Pima College Rockhounds, 1976-2010
Sub-Series 2: Miscellaneous Geology Materials, 1960-2010
Series 3: Musical Compositions,1945-2003
Series 4: Harrison Yocum Personal and Family History, 1864-2010
Sub-Series 1: Biographical Information about Harrison Yocum, 1952-2010
Sub-Series 2: Yocum Family History, 1864-2006
Sub-Series 3: Publications about and by Harrison Yocum, 2005-2009
Sub-Series 4: Large Format Objects, 2005-2009
Series 5: Audio Cassettes of Yocum's Piano Compositions, undated
Series 6: Photographs, undated
Series 7: Photo Albums, 1962-2010
Sub-Series 1: Tucson Botanical Gardens, 1962-2005
Sub-Series 2: Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds, 1997-2009
Sub-Series 3: Horticulture Newsclippings, undated
Sub-Series 4: Travel Photos of Harrison Yocum, 2002-2009
Sub-Series 5: Harrison Yocum's Family and Friends, 1961-2005
Scope and Content Note
Harrison Yocum was instrumental in the establishment of the Tucson Botanical Gardens (TBG), however the bulk of this collection focuses on his geology club, the Pima College Rockhounds; his schoolwork and independent research on botany; his piano compositions; his autobiography and family history, with some material focused on TBG.
Also housed in the collection is much history and some genealogy of the Yocum family, including correspondence from his ancestor George Seifert as well as letters and mementoes from Harrison's parents Harrison senior (Harry) and Bertha Yocum and a book about his sister, Eloise as well as materials gathered from his parents’ trip to California in 1915.
This collection is arranged by medium: documents, cassettes, photo albums. Documents are arranged topically and by date when given.
International Palm Society.; Pima Community College.; Tucson Airport Authority.; Tucson Botanical Gardens.; Botany--Arizona.; Geology--Arizona--Cochise County.; Geology--Arizona--Pima County.; Geology--New Mexico--Grant County.; Horticulture--Arizona.; Mineralogy--Arizona.; Music by American composers--in manuscript.; Palms--Arizona.; Rock collectors--United States.
Container List
- Work in Botany, 1950-2010; Series 1
  Contains academic notes, schoolwork, academic projects, independent research focused on botany.
  - 1951-1989, Subseries 1: Academic and Professional Work
    - Plant Propagation, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Agronomy Notes from Penn State Botanical Labs (1 of 2), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Agronomy Notes from Penn State Botanical Labs (2 of 2), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Geology 20, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Horticulture 8, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Horticulture 211, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Entomology 9, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Flower Arranging, Horticulture 151, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Agriculture 432, U Tenn, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ferns, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Academic Diplomas, 1935-1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Academic and Professional Publications, 1961-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Press Clippings, 1966-1996 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Professional and Academic Records, 1951-1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Academic and Professional Awards and Certifications, 1956-2001 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Garden Writers of America Manual for Writers, TV/Radio Commentators and Public Speakers, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Biblical Notes on Botany, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Work on Palm Trees, 1950-1986; Subseries 2
    - Palm Seed Record, 1950-1985 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Palm Material (1 of 4), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Palm Material (2 of 4), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Palm Material (3 of 4), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Palm Material (4 of 4), 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Re; Palms Varied Items, 1964-1993 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - International Palm Society, 1957-1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Arizona Chapter of International Palm Society, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tucson Botanical Gardens, 1964-2010; Subseries 3
    - Tucson Botanical Gardens Early Records, 1964-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Tucson Botanical Gardens Early Photos, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Plans for Tucson Botanical Gardens, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Tucson Botanical Gardens Foundational Documents, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Tucson Botanical Gardens Correspondence, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Harrison Yocum Tucson Botanical Gardens Press Clippings and Articles, 1965-2010 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Tucson Botanical Garden, Inc. Articles Published Concerning Tucson Botanical Garden Including Papers by Harrison Yocum (1 of 2), 1968-2008 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Tucson Botanical Garden, Inc. Articles Published Concerning Tucson Botanical Garden Including Papers by Harrison Yocum (2 of 2), 1968-2008 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Guides to Various Gardens (1 of 2), 1952-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Guides to Various Gardens (2 of 2), 1952-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Botanical Garden Brochures, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Work in Geology, 1976-2010; Series 2
  - Records of the Pima College Rockhounds, 1976-2010; Subseries 1
    - Perambulations of Pleasant Delights: Areas Frequented by the PIMA COLLEGE ROCK-HOUNDS (1 of 2), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Perambulations of Pleasant Delights: Areas Frequented by the PIMA COLLEGE ROCK-HOUNDS (2 of 2), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Pima College Rock-hounds Complete Records (1 of 3), 1977-2008 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Pima College Rock-hounds Complete Records (2 of 3), 1977-2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Pima College Rock-hounds Complete Records (3 of 3), 1977-2008 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Rockhound Intineraries and Maps, 1977-2008 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - A Rockhound's Handbook (Manuscript), circa 1982 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Pima College Rockhounds, 1982-2008 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Maps and Articles for the Rockhounds (1 of 2), 1988-2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Maps and Articles for the Rockhounds (2 of 2), 1988-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Pima College Rockhound Handouts, circa 1999 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - A Rockhound's Handbook(Revised), Circa 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Pima College Rockhounds Large Photos, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rock-Hounds Book no. 6, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Historical Notes on Southern Arizona, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous Geology Materials, 1960-2010; Subseries 2
    This subseries deals with Yocum's work in geology that was not directly related to the Rockhounds, including his participation in the Old Pueblo Lapidary Club.
    - Historical Background of the Old Pueblo Lapidary Club, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Catalog of Minerals, 1960-2010 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Brochures from Geology-related Destinations, circa 1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Notes on Minerals, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Musical Compositions, 1945-2003; Series 3
  Aside from work in botany and geology, Harrison Yocum studied music, the piano and composed a large number of original music, including many polkas and waltzes inspired by his observations and understanding of the natural world. Prominent among his works is the Catalina Suite in four movements, inspired by the mountain ranges surrounding Tucson.
  - Untitled
    - Opus 4 The Cardboard Mountains(Catalina Suite), 1965 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Piano Compositions (1 of 2), 1945-1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Piano Compositions (2 of 2), 1945-1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Piano Compositions (1 of 2), 1976-1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Piano Compositions (2 of 2), 1976-1989 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Piano Compositions (1 of 2), 1989-2003 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Piano Compositions (2 of 2), 1989-2003 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Autobiography and Family History of Harrison Yocum, 1952-2008; Series 4
  Harrison Yocum became a custodian of his family history while caring for his parents.
  - Biographical Information About Harrison Yocum, 1952-2008; Subseries 1
    This subseries focuses on Harrison Yocum himself, his autobiography, corrsepondence and his press clippings.
    - Autobiography of Harrison Yocum, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Harrison Yocum Press Clippings and Poems, 1956-2006 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Who's Who Entries and Press Clippings, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Harrison Yocum Autobiographical Material Sent to Penn State, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1952-2010 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence from Children, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Video Interviews with Harrison Yocum (Contains CD/ROM), 2006 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Visitors' Log from Funeral of Harrison Yocum, 2010 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Badges from Professional Societies, undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Yocum Family History, 1864-2006; Subseries 2
    A great deal of material focused on Harrison Yocum's parents and their family background were included in the papers, including documents from an ancestor dating back to the Civil War era. A few items of interest include Harrison Senior's draft notice ordering him for induction at a date two days after World War 1 ended along with an Army pamphlet warning of the dangers of "venereal disease" and publicity materials from the Yocum family's trip to California and the Panama-Pacific Exhibition in 1915.
    - Family Correspodence, 1864-1917 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Harrison Youcm Sr's Inspirational Books, circa 1900 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Yocum Family History, 1900-1999 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Tourist Literature from California, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Program from a Charles Schwab Banquet, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Harrison Yocum Sr's Draft Notice, 1918 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Family Correspondence, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Art and Life of Eloise June Johnson (nee Yocum), 2006 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Harrison Yocum and Family Large Photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Publications by and about Harrison Yocum, 2005-2009; Subseries 3
    These are full issues of magazines featuring articles about Harrison Yocum, correspondence with a writer from Rock & Gem Magazine and a book containing his poem, "Contemplations"
    - Harrison Yocum Prizes His Backyard Kingdom, Arizona Highways May 2005 (2 copies) (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Rockhounding Pioneer Harrison Yocum, Rock & Gem Magazine, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence and Manuscript re: Rock & Gem Article, 2008 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Timeless Voices contains poem by Harrison Yocum, undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Large Format Objects, 1900-2001; Subseries 4
    These larger format flat objects are arranged smallest to largest.
    - Harrison Yocum's Freemason's Apron, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Photocollage, circa 2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Confirmation Certificate for Harrison Yocum Sr., 1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Baptism Certificates of Harrison Yocum's Parents, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Artwork by Harrison Yocum, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Large Masonic Certificate, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Cassettes of Yocum's Piano Compositions, undated; Series 5
  This is a group of 20 cassettes with minimal documentation stating they are recordings of Yocum playing his compositions.
  - Cassettes of Yocum's Piano Compositions, undated (Box 5)
- Photographs, undated; Series 6
  An aggregation of unorganized photos of Harrison Yocum and his friends and Rockhounds over the years.
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6)
- Scrapbooks, 1962-2010; Series 7
  Harrison Yocum organized a number of edited and captioned scrapbooks of his life, his family, his parties and his Rockhounding expeditions. Although some are numbered sequentially, not all volumes are in the possession of our collection.
  - Tucson Botanical Gardens, 1952-2008; Subseries 1
    This subseries focuses on the development of Tucson Botanical Gardens in Yocum's backyard.
    - House and Garden of Harrison Yocum and Development at 1628 N. Jefferson Ave. original home of Tucson Botanical Gardens, 1962-1992 (Item 1)
    - House and Garden of Harrison Yocum Volume 3 “Original Home of Tucson Botanical Gardens”, 2002-2005 (Item 2)
  - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds 1997-2009, Subseries 2
    Photos of Harrison Yocum and his Rockhounds out on their field trips.
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds Volume II, 1997-1999 (Item 3)
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds Volume III, 2000-2001 (Item 4)
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds Volume IV, 2001-2002 (Item 5)
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds Volume V, 2002-2003 (Item 6)
    - Rockhounds, 2001-2010 (Item 7)
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds Volume IX, 2007 (Item 8)
    - Perambulations of the Pima College Rockhounds Volume X, 2008-2009 (Item 9)
  - Horticulture, Undated; Subseries 3
    Press clippings about horticulture.
    - Horticulture, 2008-2010 (Item 10)
  - Travel Photos, 2002-2009; Subseries 4
    Travel photos of Harrison Yocum on vacation from Europe to Alaska.
    - Heritage Album of Harrison Yocum, 2002 (Item 11)
    - Photos from a trip to the Baltic Sea, 2004 (Item 12)
    - Photos from a trip to the British Isles, 2006 (Item 13)
    - Photos from a trip to Alaska, 2009 (Item 14)
  - Harrison Yocum's Family and Friends, 1952-2008; Subseries 5
    Scrapbooks of parties and family events.
    - Party Album of Harrison Gerald Yocum “Golden Memories of my Cherished Friends” Volume I, 1986-1997 (Item 15)
    - “Golden Memories of my Cherished Friends” Volume 2, 1978-2005 (Item 16)
    - Family Scrapbook, 1961-2005 (Item 17)